Guide to the James H. Laue papers, 1936-1999
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 3: Peace Academy Campaign Papers, 1947-1990, bulk 1976-1990
  - N-PAC Briefing Summary for the U.S. Academy for Peace and Conflict Resolution, ca. 1979 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - N-PAC Brochures, 1981-1986 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - N-PAC - Bryant Wedge Memo to Campaign Members and Contributors, December 25, 1977 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - N-PAC - "But What Can the Churches Do about Peace?", ca. 1980 (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1976 (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, September 1976 - January 1977 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    contains correspondence, meeting minutes, newsletters, notes, and memoranda
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1977 (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1977 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1977 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1977-1981 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, November 13-14, 1978 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1978-1979 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Files, 1982-1985 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Update, 1977-1978 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Update, Fall 1979 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Update and News Clippings on H.R. 1249 and S. 564, Fall 1983 (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - N-PAC - Campaign Updates, 1982-1986 (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - N-PAC - Christian Science Monitor Articles, December 1981 (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - N-PAC - Coming Events Coordinated by the Washington Office, 1978 (Box 41, Folder 10)
  - N-PAC - Copy Draft for New N-PAC Brochure, ca. 1978 (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - N-PAC - DC Trip, October 1977 (Box 41, Folder 12)
  - N-PAC - "Development of a U.S. Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution: Analysis and Forecast, 1976-80", 1978-1985 (Box 41, Folder 13)
  - N-PAC - "Development of a U.S. Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution: Analysis and Forecast, 1976-80," Draft, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - N-PAC - Draft By-Laws of the National Peace Academy Campaign, February 1978 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - N-PAC - Draft Resolution Proposal to United Nations, April 1, 1977 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - N-PAC Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - N-PAC Executive Council Meeting Agenda, March 1979 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - N-PAC Executive Council Roster, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - N-PAC Expense Sheet, 1977-1978 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - N-PAC Fiscal Summary, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - N-PAC Guidelines for Receptions, ca. 1978 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - N-PAC - James Laue Resume and History of the N-PAC, 1983 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - N-PAC Legislative Fact Sheet on the Peace Academy Commission Bill, August 1978 (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - N-PAC Legislative Strategy, 1983 (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - N-PAC Memoranda, 1978-1979 (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - N-PAC Memoranda, September 1983 - October 1984 (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - N-PAC Memorandum and Bibliography, 1979-1982 (Box 42, Folder 15)
  - N-PAC Issue Paper, Winter 1978 (Box 42, Folder 16)
  - N-PAC News Summary, 1977-1978 (Box 42, Folder 17)
  - N-PAC News Summary, August 1978 (Box 42, Folder 18)
  - N-PAC Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 42, Folder 19)
  - N-PAC Organizational Components Flowchart, Memo, and Personnel, 1979 (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - N-PAC - Peace Academy Benefit, February 6, 1978, and U.N. Ambassadors, 1977-1978 (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - N-PAC - "Playing the Game to Win: Strategies and Tactics of Interest Groups in American Politics, December 1978 (Box 42, Folder 22)
    N-PAC Case Study by Regina Ceisler
  - N-PAC Press Releases and Promotional Brochures, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 23)
  - N-PAC - Proposal for Preparation of a Ford Foundation Briefing Report, July 13, 1979 (Box 42, Folder 24)
  - N-PAC Proposal for a National Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution, ca. 1976 (Box 42, Folder 25)
  - N-PAC Resumes and Personnel, 1977-1979 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - N-PAC Statements, Speeches and Press Releases on Establishing a U.S. Department of Peace, 1972-1980 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - N-PAC - "A Thumbnail History of the Campaign for a U.S. Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution", 1977 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - N-PAC - Wedge and Spencer - Papers, Action Updates, Brochure, 1976-1977 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - National Peace Academy Foundation (NPAF) - Articles / Publication, 1984-1986 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    note: items under the heading "NPAF" pertain to the financial wing of the U.S. Academy of Peace
  - NPAF - Burl and Dorothy Ives Benefit Concert, Financial, Correspondence, 1982 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - NPAF - Correspondence re: Burl Ives Benefit Concert, November - December 1982 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - NPAF - DC Trip - N-PAC Board and NPAF, 1983 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - NPAF - "Establishing the United States Institute of Peace: The Next Six Months", November 8, 1984 (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - NPAF - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes and Financial Statements, 1982-1984 (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - NPAF Files, September - October 1982 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - NPAF Files, March - May 1983 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - NPAF Files, 1983-1984 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - NPAF Files, November 1984 - January 1985 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - NPAF - Financial and Tax Exemption, 1982-1984 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - NPAF Minutes, Memos, Notes, etc., March - April 1983 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - NPAF Minutes, Memos, Notes, etc., Summer 1983 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - NPAF Minutes, Memos, Notes, etc., Summer 1983 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - NPAF / N-PAC Joint Meeting, September 1984 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - NPAF / N-PAC Merger, October 1983 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - NPAF - "The U.S. Academy of Peace: A long Step Toward Real Security", by Frank K. Kelly, 44 pages (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - "The National Peace Academy: Suggestions on Structure and Process", February 1978 (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - National Peace Education Fund (NPEF) - Briefing Report for Members of the Commission, December 1979 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - NPEF - Conflict Resolution Technique Survey, June 9, 1980 (Box 44, Folder 13)
  - NPEF - DC / NPAE (Box 44, Folder 14)
  - National Peace Institute Foundation (NPIF) - Annual Reports, 1986-1987 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    note: the National Peace Academy Foundation changed its name to the National Peace Institute Foundation in 1985
  - NPIF Board and Executive Committee Meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, 1984-1986 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, 1985-1987 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, May - June 1985 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, June - July 1965 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, December 13, 1985 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, June 19, 1986 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, September - December 1986 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, January - March 1987 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, June 19, 1987 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    includes Ralph Nader article, "Neglecting Peace"
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, December 11, 1987 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, March 18, 1988 - 1989 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - NPIF Board Meeting Minutes, 1988 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - NPIF Board Meetings of the Midwest Regional Council, part 1 of 2, July - August 1986 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - NPIF Board Meetings of the Midwest Regional Council, part 2 of 2, September 1986 - January 1986 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - NPIF - "Building Peace: A Five Year Plan", April - December 1985 (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - NPIF - Excuses for Board Members' Absence, March 1986 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - NPIF Files, 1991-1993 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - NPIF Financial Statements, 1985 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - NPIF Financial Statements, 1987 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - NPIF Journal, Vol. 1, No. 1, ca. 1985 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - NPIF Leadership Concerns, April 1986 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    alcoholism
  - NPIF - Lists of Appointments to the Board, 1985 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - NPIF Membership Survey, 1985 (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - NPIF - Peace Institute Reporter, 1986-1992 (Box 47, Folder 9)
    newsletter
  - NPIF - Peacemaking Behavior: Major Research Areas, 1986 (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - NPIF Quarterly Report, Second Quarter, August 1985 (Box 47, Folder 11)
  - NPIF - Regional Guide, Draft, ca. 1986 (Box 47, Folder 12)
  - NPIF Steering Committee, January 1985 (Box 47, Folder 13)
  - NPIF - Symposium, Ireland, October 12-21, 1985 (Box 47, Folder 14)
  - NPIF Trip to California and Hawaii; Francoise Hall, August 17 - September 8, 1985 (Box 47, Folder 15)
  - NPIF Updates, August - November 1985 (Box 47, Folder 16)
  - Peace Academy and the Committee for American-Iranian Crisis Resolution, 1979-1980 (Box 47, Folder 17)
  - Peace Academy Book Materials, part 1 of 2, 1976-1978 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Peace Academy Book Materials, part 2 of 2, 1980 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    proposal for National Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution
  - "A Peace Academy May Be Coming", November 24, 1978 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    Focal Point
  - Peace and Change: A Journal of Peace Research, Author and Subject Index, Vols. 1-3 and Vol. 8, No. 2/3, Summer 1977; Summer 1982 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Peace Research Journal, 1982, 1991 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution - Miscellaneous Journals and Newsletters, 1988-1991 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - "Peacemaking: Strategies and Skills for Just Resolution of Conflict", April 1981 (Box 48, Folder 7)
    by James Laue, printed in Engage / Social Action
  - "Peacemaking Without Division", 1986 (Box 48, Folder 8)
    by Patricia Washburn and Robert Gribbon
  - "A Plan of a Peace-Office for the United States", 1947 (Box 48, Folder 9)
    by Benjamin Rush, first published in 1789
  - Pre-Publication Draft: For Women's International Feminist Quarterly - "Perspectives of Women Researchers on Disarmament", ca. 1979 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    by Elise Boulding
  - Promoting "... The Peaceful Resolution of International Conflict": Contributions of the Emerging Field of Conflict Resolution, ca. 1986 (Box 48, Folder 11)
  - "Resistance to the Idea of a Peace Institute: an idea 'loved to death'", 1977 (Box 48, Folder 12)
    by Joseph H. Herzberg
  - Sermon - "Christians and the U.S. Peace Academy: Is There a Future?", November 21, 1982 (Box 48, Folder 13)
  - Sermon - "Xian and the U.S. Academy of Peace", May 23 - July 25, 1982 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    Cleveland, Ohio; Albert L. Jeandheur
  - "Study Group Report Calls for Founding U.S. Peace Academy", September 26, 1980 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    St. Louis Review
  - The Survival of Andy Young, August 8, 1979 (Box 48, Folder 16)
  - Terrorism: A Peace Academy Can Help, May 1978 (Box 48, Folder 17)
  - To Move the Whole Future, March 1979 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    by Milton C. Mapes in Anthropology and Humanism Quarterly
  - "Toward a Peacekeeping Academy," Early Draft, September 1981 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    by Arthur I. Waskow
  - United States Academy of Peace (USAP) - MLK Center Dedication Speech and Notes, ca. 1982 (Box 48, Folder 20)
  - United States Institute of Peace (USIP) Board Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    note: the U.S. Academy of Peace changed its name to the U.S. Institute of Peace in 1984
  - USIP Board Meeting, February 25-26, 1986 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - USIP Board Meeting, February 25-26, 1986 (Box 49, Folder 3)
    revised agenda
  - USIP Board Meeting, April 1986 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - USIP Board Meeting, September 18, 1986 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - USIP Board Meeting, January - March 1987 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - USIP Board of Directors - Questions for Candidates, December 1985 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - USIP Briefing, December 11, 1984 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - USIP - "Dialogues on Conflict Resolution: Bridging Theory and Practice", 1993 (Box 49, Folder 9)
    by W. Scott Thompson, James Laue, Brian Urquhart, and Chester A. Crocker
  - USIP Grants, ca. 1984 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - USIP Journal, 1988-1993 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    newsletter of the USIP
  - USIP - Letters of Endorsement for Laue's Nomination to the Board of Directors, February - March 1985 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - USIP Miscellaneous Files, 1985 (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - USIP Newsletters and Brochures, 1986-1990 (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - USIP Program Update, February 27, 1987 (Box 49, Folder 15)
  - USIP - PoN SC, February 3, 1987 (Box 49, Folder 16)
  - William and Flora Hewlett Foundation, May 11, 1978; February 13, 1979 (Box 49, Folder 17)
  - William and Flora Hewlett Foundation Grant, 1986-1987 (Box 49, Folder 18)
  - Waging Peace: Working Together on National Security and Arms Control, 1985 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    a project of the Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs of the University of Minnesota in cooperation with the Committee for National Security, Honeywell, Inc., and the League of Women Voters of Minnesota; 104 pages
  - We Can Have Peace!, ca. 1977 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    by Bryant Wedge
  - Why a Department of Peace?, 1969 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    by Frederick L. Schuman
  - Young, Andrew - "The Young Mission," Saturday Review, and "Young's Leaving Has Obscured His Policy Successes," Washington Post, July 9, 1977; August 26, 1979 (Box 50, Folder 4)
- Series 4: Civil Rights Papers, 1956-1988
  This series documents Laue's involvement in the Civil Rights movement during the 1960s. The series is divided into two subseries. Subseries 4.1, Direct Action and Desegregation, covers Laue's activism in the Civil Rights movement during the early 1960s and includes notes, interviews, and other materials used in his dissertation, Direct Action and Desegregation, 1960-1962 as well as later essays on Civil Rights by Laue and others. This subseries also contains memoranda, pamphlets, and newsletters from such prominent Sixties grass-roots organizations as the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), the Southern Regional Council (SRC), and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). Subseries 4.2, Community Relations Service (CRS), documents Laue's work for the CRS under the U.S. Department of Justice in the mid to late 1960s, where he became the head of Program Evaluation and Development. Materials include reports, meeting minutes, correspondence, personnel files, and speeches.
  - Subseries 4.1: Direct Action and Desegregation, 1956-1988, bulk 1960-1969
    This subseries covers Laue's activism in the Civil Rights movement during the early 1960s and includes notes, interviews, and other materials used in his dissertation, Direct Action and Desegregation, 1960-1962 as well as later essays on Civil Rights by Laue and others. This subseries also contains memoranda, pamphlets, and newsletters from such prominent Sixties grass-roots organizations as the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), the Southern Regional Council (SRC), and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    - "Afterword: New York City in 1970" (Box 50, Folder 5)
      by Nathan Glazer and Daniel P. Moynihan, 103 pages
    - American Child, Vol. 47, No. 4: "Which Way Community Action Programs?", November 1965 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, March and July 1969 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Albany, Georgia I - Article Draft, 1961-1962 (Box 50, Folder 8)
      includes notes, news clippings, and a pamphlet on the civil rights movement in Albany prepared by Students for a Democratic Society
    - Albany, Georgia II - General, 1962 (Box 50, Folder 9)
      includes notes, news clippings, and an essay on Albany by Howard Zinn, prepared for the Southern Regional Council
    - Albany, Georgia III - Anecdotal, 1962 (Box 50, Folder 10)
      includes notes, news clippings, and information on a Prayer Pilgrimage in Albany on August 27
    - Articles on Racial Conflict and Mediation, 1965-1988 (Box 50, Folder 11)
      articles by James Laue
    - "The Association of Southern Women for the Prevention of Lynching: A Commentary on the Role of the 'Moderate'", 1965 (Box 51, Folder 1)
      by James Laue and Leon McCorkle
    - Atlanta, 1960-1961 (Box 51, Folder 2)
      includes a special report from the Southern Regional Council titled, "Plans for Progress: Atlanta Survey"
    - Atlanta Conference with Ministers, February 1961 (Box 51, Folder 3)
      contains notes for a talk titled "Atlanta: on Church and Power Structure"
    - The Black Law Journal, Vol. 1, No. 2, Summer 1971 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Black Manifesto, etc., 1969-1970 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - The Black Movement: A Social History of Protest in the '60s, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 6)
      revised draft by Martin Oppenheimer and James Laue, 150 pages
    - Black Panthers, 1969 (Box 51, Folder 7)
      magazine examining the Black Panther movement, edited by Patricia Sachs, written by J. Alvin Kugelmass, published by Universal Publishing and Distributing Corporation
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 1 and Introduction, 1969 (Box 51, Folder 8)
      by James Laue and Martin Oppenheimer; annotated manuscript drafts with revisions and comments
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 2 - "Theories of Social Movements", 1967-1969 (Box 51, Folder 9)
      by James Laue and Martin Oppenheimer; manuscript draft with comments
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 3 - "Movements as Systems: A Dynamic Approach", 1967-1969 (Box 51, Folder 10)
      chapter notes and outlines
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 4 - The AM Case, ca. 1967 (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 5 - "The Desegregation Process to 1960", 1969 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 6 - "Charisma", 1969 (Box 51, Folder 13)
      manuscript draft with comments; portion derived from Laue's dissertation, "Direct Action and Desegregation"
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 6d, 7? (Box 51, Folder 14)
      annotated partial manuscript draft
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 7 - "Freedom Rides", ca. 1969 (Box 51, Folder 15)
      manuscript revision later included as chapter 5 of Laue's published dissertation
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 8 - Albany and Atlanta, ca. 1969 (Box 51, Folder 16)
      manuscript revision later included as chapter 6 of Laue's published dissertation
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 9 - Nationalization of the Movement, ca. 1969 (Box 51, Folder 17)
      manuscript draft with notes
    - Black Protest Book Manuscript, Chapter 10, 1969 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      manuscript draft with comments
    - The Black Scholar: Journal of Black Studies and Research, September 1970 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Black United Front, Boston, 1970-1971 (Box 52, Folder 3)
      includes correspondence with Rev. John P. Adams and a letter from the Black United Front rejecting Laue's proposal for a Community Crisis Intervention Project
    - Black Workers in Revolt: Detroit's Black Revolutionary Workers, 1969 (Box 52, Folder 4)
      by Robert Dudnick
    - Book Chapter Skips and Appendices, ca. 1969 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Book with Oppenheimer, 1966-1967 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Book with Oppenheimer - Hottest Working Folder, 1964-1968 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Burke Marshall Profile from Life Magazine, August 9, 1963 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - The Care and Feeding of Power Structures Revisited, 1967 (Box 52, Folder 9)
      pamphlet by Jack Minnis; Organizer's Library Series of the Southern Conference Educational Fund
    - Carol Waymon, 1968-1974 (Box 52, Folder 10)
      file includes a pamphlet of the Network on Educational Unrest, surveys on racial perceptions, and a paper titled "The Corp: Its Role, Its Ethics, Its Ideology"
    - "The Changing Character of Negro Protest", January 1965 (Box 52, Folder 11)
      article reprinted from the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science
    - Childe Development Group of Mississippi (CDGM), 1966 (Box 52, Folder 12)
      includes newsletters, memoranda, news clippings, reports, and community resource packets
    - The Christian Century, February 1971 (Box 52, Folder 13)
      cover story on student activism, by Robert C. Johansen
    - Church and Race, 1960-1961 (Box 52, Folder 14)
      contains articles, sermons, notes, news clippings, and meeting minutes from the Fisk Institute on Race Relations
    - Citizens' Council, 1958-1961 (Box 52, Folder 15)
      includes newspapers, journals, and public addresses published by the Citizens' Council, as well as an op-ed to the Washington Post, written by Charleton Putnam
    - Citizenship Clinic Manual for Georgia Voter Registration, 1962 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Civil Rights in Nashville, Tennessee; Birmingham, Alabama; and Kentucky Cities, ca. 1962 (Box 52, Folder 17)
      includes pamphlet from the Nashville Christian Leadership Council, a pro-desegregation letter to department store presidents from students of Miles College in Birmingham, and a pamphlet titled "Committees on Human Rights in Kentucky"
    - Civil Rights Notebook, 1962 (Box 53, Folder 1)
      contains Laue's notes on the Civil Rights movement
    - Civil Rights Notebook - Atlanta Sit-Ins, October 13-19, 1960 (Box 53, Folder 2)
      contains Laue's notes on department store sit-ins in Atlanta
    - Civil Rights Notebooks, ca. 1960 (Box 53, Folder 3)
      contain Laue's notes on the Civil Rights movement
    - Comment: A Monthly Journal of Informed Opinion, Vol. 2, No. 1, October 1961 (Box 53, Folder 4)
      published by the Harvard Political Participation Council
    - "Community Organizing and the War on Poverty", November 1965 (Box 53, Folder 5)
      article by Tom Hayden in Liberation
    - Congress on Racial Equality (CORE) Annual Convention, July 3-5, 1964 - Letter from Martin Oppenheimer, July 7, 1964 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - "A CORE Charge to the White House Conference", November 17-18, 1965 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - CORE Conference, St. Louis, July 1960 (Box 53, Folder 7)
      includes newsletters, memoranda, notes, and correspondence
    - CORE - Miami CORE Institute, August 1960 (Box 53, Folder 10)
      includes notes, news clippings, a criminal probation notice to James Laue from the Court of Dade County, Florida, for civil disobedience, and a probation discharge notice the following year
    - CORE - "The Right to Vote", August 1962 (Box 53, Folder 11)
      pamphlet with photographs, by James T. McCain, CORE Director of Organization
    - "A Contemporary Revitalization Movement in American Race Relations: The 'Black Muslims'", March 1964 (Box 53, Folder 12)
      article by James Laue published in Social Forces Vol. 42, No. 3, pp. 315-24
    - Content Analysis - Notes, February 1962 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Crusade for Citizenship - Tuskeegee Civic Association, 1958-1961 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Current, 1963 (Box 53, Folder 15)
      three issues
    - "Desegregation in the St. Louis Public Schools: Brown and Beyond", 1979 (Box 53, Folder 16)
      by Richard Patton and James Laue
    - Direct Action and Desegregation, A. Intro and Chapters 1 and 2, ca. 1962 (Box 53, Folder 17)
      from dissertation by James Laue
    - Direct Action and Desegregation, C. The Theory: The Rationalization of Protest, Chapter 7, ca. 1962 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Direct Action and Desegregation, Chapter 8, ca. 1962 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - Direct Action and Desegregation, Chapter 9 and Appendix, ca. 1962 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Discrimination in Housing - Miscellaneous Publications, 1964-1967 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Dissertation Manuscript Drafts with Revisions, ca. 1963-1965 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Dissertation Summary, 1965 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - The Emergence of Black Power, 1965 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Emergency Public Integration Committee (EPIC) - Woolworth's Sit-Ins, etc., 1960 (Box 54, Folder 8)